Guide to the Robert Evans Alexander papers, 1935-1993
Alexander, Robert Evans papers, 1935-1993
- Photostat of 13., 14 (Box 107)
- BHV article in Journal of Housing Apr. 1966, 15 (Box 107)
- "Village Green". Change ownership to condominiums, 1975., 16 (Box 107)
- BHV Reports to Board of directors 1942-1946 (I was a Board Member), 17 (Box 107)
- BHV revisited in Progressive Architecture, May 1949, Mar. 1949, Jan. 1951, 18 (Box 107)
- BHV 25 year Award AIR 1972 followed Cranbrook School by Perkins & Will (Sadriner Consultant) and Rockefeller Center (Harrison), 19 (Box 107)
- Wilson, Merrill & Alexander, 20 (Box 107)
  Naive brochure, 1940
- Production Control Report 1944 (my first job at Lockheed during WWII), 21 (Box 107)
- Estrada Courts 1939. First known as "Hunter St. Project.", 22 (Box 107)
- Earliest design awards in 1934 & 1935, 23 (Box 107)
- Operation Retread, 24 (Box 107)
  First attempt to up-date arch. education, organized by REA for So. Cal. Chapter AIA.
- UCLA Conference on Indoor Environment; REA paper on Page 31, 25 (Box 107)
- A New Look for the City - Los Angeles 1950., 26 (Box 107)
  A study of redevelopment problems in L.A. Manuscript including first part published by Haynes Foundation.
- The Rural City, 27 (Box 107)
  Report of mission to India by REA for United Nations, 1951. Reported to Tech Assistant Admin., 1952.
- Bunkers Comeback, 28 (Box 107)
  Article on Bunker Hill Towers 1968
- Redevelopment Plan Report Sacramento 1950, 29 (Box 107)
  First collaboration Neutra & Alexander.
- Planning Process Behind the Blueprint, 30 (Box 107)
  Article by REA in 1948-1949 edition American School & University, re University Elementary Demonstration School at UCLA.
- Report on Development Plan Y Construction Program for Orange Coast College, Jan. 8, 1951., 31 (Box 107)
- Orange Coast College Landscape Plan - Garrett Eckbo., 32 (Box 107)
- Separation of Neutra & Alexander - my move to Mobil Bldg., 33 (Box 107)
- A Desert Counselling Center at Ridgecrest, CA 1975., 34 (Box 107)
- Cry California magazine - article page 7 by REA - "Too Little Too Late Too Bad" on transit, Spring 1968., 35 (Box 107)
- Instant Transit, 36 (Box 107)
  Proposal by REA resulting in minibus system for Los Angeles CBD, 1969.
- The Court of Man, 37 (Box 107)
  REA concept proposed for Caltech
- Anchorage at the Crossroads Aug. 1964, 38 (Box 107)
  Proposal to replan & rebuild Anchorage, Alaska CBD after earthquake.
- Hall of Records presentation, Mar. 3, 1957., 39 (Box 107)
- Environmental Quality & Amenity in California, Mar. 1966., 1 (Box 108)
- Norwalk Planning Study phase I, 1969., 2 (Box 108)
- Norwalk Planning Study phase II, 1969., 3 (Box 108)
- Century Freeway East of 605? (Impact on Norwalk), 4 (Box 108)
- New Vistas of Vista - general plan for Community Development, 1966., 5 (Box 108)
- City of Vista Zoning Ordinance Proposal, 1966., 6 (Box 108)
- City of Vista Subdivision Proposal., 7 (Box 108)
- City of Vista Capital Improvement Program, 1966., 8 (Box 108)
- Viva San Fernando general plan, 1968., 9 (Box 108)
- San Fernando Airport? 1967, 10 (Box 108)
- Where should a Civic Center be Located? 1968, 11 (Box 108)
- Reading the Palm of Escondido 1960, 12 (Box 108)
  First attempt by REA under 701 program. Entirely personal work of REA.
- El Paso Development Manual, 1968., 13 (Box 108)
- Projected Land Uses & Public Facilities in El Paso, 1967., 14 (Box 108)
- Large Parcel Ownership in El Paso, 1967., 15 (Box 108)
- El Paso Libraries, Police Dept., Mass Transit, 1967., 16 (Box 108)
- Land Use & Zoning - El Paso, 1965., 17 (Box 108)
- A Short History of Yoleta - El Paso, 1966., 18 (Box 108)
- A Short History of Northeast El Paso, 1966., 19 (Box 108)
- Public Facilities in El Paso, 1967., 20 (Box 108)
- Selected Areas in El Paso with Problems of Special Significance, 1964., 21 (Box 108)
- West End Urban Renewal - Stockton Redevelopment., 22 (Box 108)
- Proposal for Santa Monica - joint venture with Kelly & Grugen., 23 (Box 108)
- Fallout Shelter Survey - pilot project, 1959 (Part I), 24 (Box 108)
- Fallout Shelter Survey, 25 (Box 108)
  Part II procedures & operating experience - one of 4 pilot surveys under Eisenhower admin.
- Mono County Center space study & master plan, 1973., 26 (Box 108)
- City of Emeryville general plan and draft EIR, 27 (Box 108)
- Residence for Dr. Morton Lee Pearce, 1954., 28 (Box 108)
- Thousand Oaks Multiple Development proposal, 1971., 29 (Box 108)
- Behavioral Biology Laboratory - Caltech, 1971., 30 (Box 108)
- International Student Center near UCLA, 1960., 31 (Box 108)
- Office Bldg. for Hydril Co. project, 1971., 32 (Box 108)
- Report to the L.A. County Jr. College District, 1970., 33 (Box 108)
- White Oaks Country Club proposal, 1970., 34 (Box 108)
- UCSD College of Medicine Medical School Reports, 35 (Box 108)
  June Report on visits to several colleges of medicine in the south & east of U.S. preparing for design of UCSD complex.
- Similar report on West Coast Colleges of Medicine Feb. 19, 36 (Box 108)
- UCSD prelim report on Long Range Development Plan, 37 (Box 108)
- UCSD Graphics Master Plan Report, 38 (Box 108)
- UCSD Graphics Master Plan Report interim, Feb. 14, 1963., 39 (Box 108)
- Long Range Development Plan UCSD Oct. 1963, 40 (Box 108)
- Trumpets at the College of Jericho, June 1960, commencement address, Rhode Island School of Design, 41 (Box 108)
- Robert E. Alexander FAIA & Associates Brochure, 1970, 42 (Box 108)
- Gestalt Poems and Others by REA, 1975-1980, 43 (Box 108)
- Creativity Study, May 1959 at U.C. Berkeley, 44 (Box 108)
- Personality Correlates of Creativity - study of American Architecture, 45 (Box 108)
- Genus Architectus Creatora Variefas Americanus, 46 (Box 108)
- Guidelines for Preservation, Restoration and Alteration to the Central Library of Los Angeles, 47 (Box 108)
- Newsclips re Central Library & war to save it, 48 (Box 108)
- Letters - trip to India, 1951, 49 (Box 108)
- Checkpoint Charlie, 1989 (anecdotes), 50 (Box 108)
- Architecture, Planning and Social Responsibility (Box 118)
  2 volume, 800 page REA oral history published by UCLA
- Volume 1 - 8x10 photos of REA work
  - Baldwin Hills Village 1935-1942 (R.D. Johnson, Wilson, Merrill & Alexander) (Box 110)
  - Baldwin Hills Village Shops 1946-1950 (Box 110)
  - Baldwin Hills Village School 1947-1949 (Box 110)
  - Pierce Residence 1948 (Box 110)
  - University Elementary Demonstration School 1948 (Box 110)
  - Orange Coast College 1948-1955 (Box 110)
  - Mission to India 1951 (Box 110)
- Volume 2 - 8x10 photos of Neutra & Alexander work
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America Headquarters 1954 (Box 111)
  - Alamitos Junior High School 1959 (Box 111)
  - Children's Museum, Dayton, Ohio 1955 (Box 111)
  - Fine Arts Building, University of Nevada, Reno 1958 (Box 111)
  - Palos Verdes High School 1958 (Box 111)
  - Planning Professions Building 1952 (Box 111)
  - Fine Arts Building, San Fernando State University 1958 (Box 111)
  - San Pedro Hotel 1953 (Box 111)
  - Ferro-Chemical Office Building 1957 (Box 111)
  - Gettysburg Visitors' Center 1958 (Box 111)
  - Territory of Guam 1952-1954 (Box 111)
  - Los Angeles County Hall of Records (with others) 1958 (Box 111)
  - Family Housing, Lemoore Naval Air Station 1958 (Box 111)
  - U.S. State Department Chancery, Karachi, Pakistan 1957 (Box 111)
  - Chapel, Miramar Naval Air Station 1957 (Box 111)
  - Family Housing, AFB, Mountain Home, Idaho 1954 (Box 111)
  - Ticktocker Child Guidance Clinic 1954 (Box 111)
- Volume 3 - 8x10 photos of REA work
  - Franklin D. Roosevelt Memorial Competition Entry 1959 (Box 112)
  - Mount Hollywood Project 1961 (Box 112)
  - Central Library, University of Nevada, Reno 1959 (Box 112)
  - Great Western Savings & Loan, (with SOM) 1961 (Box 112)
  - Catskill Elementary School 1961 (Box 112)
  - International Student Center, Westwood 1961 (Box 112)
  - Married Student Housing, USC 1963 (Box 112)
  - U. of California, San Diego, Long Range Development Plan 1962 (Box 112)
  - U. of California, San Diego, Residence & Dining Halls 1962 (Box 112)
  - U. of California, San Diego, College of Medicine 1964-1971 (Box 112)
- Volume 4 - 8x10 photos of REA work
  - Post Earthquake CBD studies of Anchorage, Alaska 1964 (Box 113)
  - Plan for South San Diego 1963 (Box 113)
  - Bunker Hill Towers 1965-1969 (Box 113)
  - Bunker Hill Hotel studies 1968-1969 (Box 113)
  - TWA World Trade Center studies 1970 (Box 113)
  - Baxter Hall of the Humanities & Social Sciences, Caltech 1972 (Box 113)
  - Carson City Hall (with Sata & Kennard) 1976 (Box 113)
  - Santa Ana Police Facilities Building (with Neutra) 1958 (Box 113)
  - Saint John's College, Annapolis, Md. (with Neutra) (Box 113)
- Volume 5 - 35 mm slides of REA work
  - Bunker Hills Towers (Box 114)
  - Hydril Office Building studies, Dallas, Texas (Box 114)
  - Cal Poly Student Health Center (with Robert E. Clark) (Box 114)
  - Pershing Square Competition (Box 114)
  - Mono County Courthouse Addition (with Robert E. Clark) (Box 114)
  - Carson City Hall (with Frank Sata & Robert Kennard) (Box 114)
- Volume 6 - 35 mm slides of REA work
  - UCSD Long Range Development Plan (Box 115)
  - UCSD Residence Halls (Box 115)
  - Bank of America, San Bernardino Branch (Box 115)
  - UCSD College of Medicine (Box 115)
  - California Institute of Technology (Box 115)
  - LRDP for the Claremont Colleges (Box 115)
  - LRDP for Caltech (Box 115)
  - Caltech Baxter Humanities Building & Ramo Lecture Hall (Box 115)
  - Caltech consulting work (Box 115)
- Volume 7 - 35 mm slides of REA work
  - Damman Hotel studies (with Frank Sata) (Box 116)
  - South San Diego Studies (Box 116)
  - FDR Memorial Competition (Box 116)
  - Gettysburg Cyclorama Building (with Neutra) (Box 116)
  - Married Student Housing, USC (Box 116)
  - Library, Simpson College, Indianola, Iowa (with Neutra) (Box 116)
  - Chapel, Miramar Naval Air Station (with Neutra) (Box 116)
  - Theater, Camp Pendleton (Box 116)
  - L.A. County Hall of Records (with Neutra & others) (Box 116)
  - Ticktocker Nursery School (with Neutra) (Box 116)
  - 8x10 Photos of Mono County Courthouse Addition (with Bob Clark) 1975 (Box 116)
  - 8x10 Photos of Cal Poly Student Health Center (with Bob Clark) 1976 (Box 116)
- FOIPA File (Box 117)
  Correspondence with the FBI in attempt to obtain their file on REA and the results.
- Television program about a California state penitentiary volunteer program, 609 (Box 161)
- Box 119-121
  Letters from India & photographs ( 1951 UN Project)
  Professional Biographical material
  Brasilia trip
  Remaining professional correspondence
  Kurt Meyer file
  P.A.E. (Pacific Architects & Engineers) file
  Temple of Contemplation
  LA City Planning
  UCLA Demonstration School
  Misc. catalogs
  "Why LA?"
  Baldwin Hills Village (Village Green)
  Baldwin Hills Village slides
  Slides of trip to German Republic
  Tube: Copy AIA 25 yr awards, copies of statement of gratitude to Village Green & D. Wong, poem "Youth"
  Football photo from NY Times, probably 1928
- Flat Plans
  - General
    - 24 drawings and photographs of Adelphi College plans (Box 163)
    - Hollywood Riviera Methodist Church (Mapcase-folder 1 (see also rolled plans))
    - Hollywood-Riviera-Chicago (1957) (Mapcase-folder 3)
    - Mount Hollywood (Mapcase-folder 4 (see also rolled plans))
    - Blueprint copies of Thousand Gardens and Baldwin Hills Village (Mapcase-folder 2)
    - Roll of Baldwin Hills Village plans, white print copies, 1940, 1966, 1972. Plans of Alexander's Los Angeles office, The Bradbury Bldg., 1969. Thousand Gardens, Village Green. (Mapcase-folder 6)
    - Temple of Contemplation (9 pieces) (Mapcase-folder 8)
    - Architectural Drawings; plans for a multicultural restaurant (Mapcase-folder 7)
  - International Student Center, UCLA. Drawings
    - 3 Yellow tissue sketches of courtyard (Mapcase-folder 12)
    - 4 Study plans of courtyard dining area (Mapcase-folder 12)
    - 2 First Floor Plan (photocopies - 2 different reductions) (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 Basement Floor Plan (photocopy) (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 Site Plan, Roof Plan & Drawing Index (photocopy) (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 Column and Roof Shell Details (Mapcase-folder 10)
  - Presentation Set:
    - 2 drafts of introduction or statement of purpose (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 architect's identification (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - On white tracing paper: 1 basement plan (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 site plan (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 1st floor plan (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 2nd floor plan (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 section looking east (Mapcase-folder 10)
    - 1 2nd floor perspective (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Westwood International Center schematic drawing (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Westwood International Center Plot Plan (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Westwood International Center Preliminary Plans and space allotment (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Westwood International Center Preliminary Plans (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Project Sign (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Revised Doors @ Cabinet Rm. 121 (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Sketch Layout for Lounge & Dining Room Occupancy Signs (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Dormitory perspectives (Mapcase-folder 11)
    - 1 Westwood International Student Center Prelim. Plans & space allotment (Mapcase-folder 11)
  - 5 plans (set) yellow paper
    - 1 ground floor plan (Mapcase-folder 12)
    - 1 basement floor plan (Mapcase-folder 12)
    - 1 second floor plan (Mapcase-folder 12)
    - 1 sections & elevations (Mapcase-folder 12)
    - 1 sections (Mapcase-folder 12)
  - Done by ACCO (Air Conditioning Co., Inc.)
    - 1 H. Water Piping Schematic blueprint (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Wiring and Control Diagram (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Underground Exhaust Ducts (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Basement Equipment Room Layout (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Basement Opening Layout (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Basement Floor Duct Layout (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 First Floor Openings (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Second Floor Layout (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Roof Plan Openings (Mapcase-folder 9)
  - Miscellany (small pieces)
    - 1 transparency of all floor plans (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 transparency of bldg. name & address (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 study plan of roof screen enclosures (photocopy?) (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 plan of project sign (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 drawing of assorted ellipses (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 bldg. space allotment figures (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 vent. ducts (?) cross section & long. section on tissue (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 basement garage plan w/watermains (?) on waxed paper by Cosco Fire Protection Inc. (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 photocopied/reduced plan of basement floor (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 photocopied/reduced plan of second floor (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Topographic Survey by Jennings Eng. Co. (Mapcase-folder 9)
    - 1 Elevations & Kitchen Equipment - Elevations and sections (Mapcase-folder 9)
  - 11 opaque waxed drawings by Alexander/Boris Lemos Consulting Mech. Engs.
    - 1 Plumbing Basement As built (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Plumbing 1st floor As built (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Heating & Vent Basement As built (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Heating & Vent 1st floor As built (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Heating & Vent 2nd floor As built (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Heating & Vent sections & details (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Plot plan, single line diagram & symbol list (electrical) (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Basement lighting & power plan (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 1st floor lighting & power plan (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 2nd floor lighting & power plan (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Electrical - revised electrical plan for kitchen (yellow waxed) (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 Plan & schedule of equipment for kitchen (plan #C-2) (yellow waxed) (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 study plan - roof screen enclosures (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - 1 1st floor plan (Terrazzo layout) & schedule of equipment (Mapcase-folder 5)
- Rolled Plans
  - San Diego-Inland Bay Study (Box 122, 158, 160, 161)
  - San Diego-topo map-Pueblo Lands (Box 157)
  - San Diego-border area (Box 159)
  - Central Avenue (Box 123)
  - Hollywood (Box 124)
  - Mount Hollywood; Giffith Starland - Los Angeles (Box 142, 147, 155)
  - Hollywood Riviera Methodist Church (Box 152)
  - Painted Desert (Box 125, 129-137)
  - California Institute of Technology-Cal Tech (Box 126)
  - Cal Tech-Humanities Building (Box 149)
  - University of Nevada-Fine Arts Building (Box 155)
  - University of Nevada-Reno Campus Library (Box 138-139, 141, 144, 150)
  - Madras Project (Box 140)
  - Villiage Center-Concept Maps (Box 143)
  - Gettysburg (Box 127-128, 145-146)
  - Claremont, CA-Methodist Church and LA shelter survey (Box 151)
  - Santa Ana, CA-Civic Center; Dayton Museum of Natural History (Box 153)
  - Neighborhood Concept for Planned Development and miscellaneous plan (Box 154)
  - Chealsea Promonade (Box 156)
- Microfilm
  - Neutra and Alexander. Los Angeles, California. Engineering Drawings, 1950s.
    - Job No. 5053-04 S-21 to Job No. 5053-04 S-11 (Reel 1)
    - Hall of Records - #21 thru Ozalids to Hall of Records-Elec. Drawings #E-2 (Reel 2)
    - Elec. Drawings Cont #E-19 to Claremont Methodist Church #E-2 (Reel 3)
    - Dayton Museum #1-A thru #E-1 to South Elementary School #L-1 (Reel 4)
    - O.C.C. Speech Arts Buildings 101 to Cal-Ec-2 (Reel 5)
    - Cal-4-11 Site Plan to Spanish Army Housing Units (Reel 6)
    - Drawing No. 45-02-12 (Yuma Test Station) to Drawing No. 25-04-0 Sheet No. 19 Yuma Test Station (Reel 7)
    - Drawing No. 7602 - UCLA Nursery-Kindergarten to Drawing No. 8 - UCLA Nursery-Kindergarten (Reel 7a)
    - 2-8-57 Exp.? Density Test (Reel 8)
    - December 19, 1955 (Reel 9)
  - Robert E. Alexander and Associates.
    - F.Y. 1955 Military Housing (Reel 10)
    - Catskill May 9, 1963 (Reel 11)
    - International Student Center Working Drawings (Reel 12)
    - Group I Central Facilities Building (Reel 13)
    - Group II Residence Halls Unit I. (Reel 14)
    - Basic Science UCSD (Reel 15)
    - Cal. Tech Humanities Building, All Bid Documents (Reel 16)
    - Crenshaw Office, Southern California Gas Bid, August 20, 1968 (Reel 17)